天堂电影院
是  萨尔瓦托  迪·维塔·萨尔瓦托
Yes, Salvatore di Vita.
您怎么会不认识  小姐
You mean you don't know him, Miss?
没错  我是他的妈妈
That's right, and I'm his mother.
我正从西西里岛打来  整整一天
I've been calling from Sicily, all day long.
我明白  不在
I see … he's not there.
那么  您能给我…
Could you please give me his number?
65622056
656 22 056.
谢谢 日安
Thank you. Goodbye.
妈  电话没用的
It's useless to call.
他太忙了  谁知道在哪里
He's busy. God knows where he is.
他也不会记得
He won't even remember.
听我的  算了吧
Forget it.
他已经30年没有回来了
He hasn't been here for 30 years.
-你知道怎么做  -不
You know what he's like.
他记得
He'll remember.
我确定他记得  我比你更了解他
I'm sure he will. I know him better than you do.
如果之后他发现我们没有告诉他  他会失望的
If he finds out we didn't tell him, he'll be angry.
请问  我能和迪·维塔·萨尔瓦托先生说话吗  我是他的母亲
I'd like to talk to Signor Salvatore di Vita. I'm his mother.
你他妈的看什么看
What the fuck are you looking at?
萨尔瓦托  几点了
Salvatore … what time is it?
很晚了
It's late.
对不起  但...  我没能提前通知你我回不来了
Sorry, I couldn't phone to say I'd be late.
睡吧
Go back to sleep.
你母亲打电话来了
Your mother phoned.
她把我当成另一个人
She thought I was someone else.
你对她说什么了
What did you tell her?
我装作没事  为了不让她失望  我们说了很长时间
Nothing, I didn't want to disappoint her. We had a long chat.
她说你有30年没有回去看她了
She said you've not visited her for 30 years.
还说当她想见你的时候她应该来罗马
She must come to see you.
她打电话就是为了跟你说这个
She called just to say that?
不  她还说有个叫艾佛特的人死了
No, she said someone's died. Someone called Alfredo.
明天是他的葬礼
The funeral is tomorrow.
他是谁  你亲戚吗
Who is he? A relative?
不  不是  睡吧  睡吧
No … go back to sleep.
真是我的灾难  我该怎么做
How can I say Mass with this boy?
旧约圣经诗歌智慧书第五卷雅歌第二节第十六章
这是我的血杯
新和永恒的盟约  信念之谜
为你而...
多多
Toto!
为你而建...
赦免罪过
还好
Thank God for that!
我怎么跟你说的
How do I have to tell you?
没有铃声  我不知道怎么向前进行
Without the bell, I don't know where I am.
你总是睡觉  你晚上干什么  睡觉的时候吃饭吗
Always asleep! What do you do at night? Eat?
我家中午不吃饭
Father Adelfio, at home we don't even eat at lunchtime.
兽医也是这么说的  所以我总是困
The vet says that's why I'm tired.
我知道你为什么困  不要以为我不知道
I'll tell you why you're tired. Think I don't know?
现在你做件好事  你走开  我有事要做
Run along now, I've something to do.
-我能进来吗  -不  你不能进来  好吧
- Can I come with you? - No, you can't.
-多多 出去  -我想进来
Toto, go away!
够了  你不能进来  出去  走开
艾佛特
Alfredo!
在
你可以开始了
You can start.
我们画个十字  然后开始
Here we go again.
屏幕
The frame!
你大早上睡着了吗
较低的深度
THE LOWER DEPTHS
佩佩  总有一天一切都是我们的
One day, everything will be ours.
我们一起离开  为自己而活
We'll go away together.
过上好日子
To live the good life …
没人知道我们从哪里来
… where no one knows us.
别做梦了  一点用都没有
Stop dreaming.
你不像原来那样爱我了
You don't love me any more.
为什么
Why?
我给你带了一个橙子和一些香烟
我宁愿一句好话
I'd have preferred a good word.
我不能  好吧
- I can't. - Oh, well.
一双  再一双  两双100里拉  弹力纱织的袜子
100 lire! Pure nylon!
快来
失败的产物
你不应该来这里
You mustn't come here.
我该怎么让你明白
How many times do I have to tell you?
我该怎么说
You're only little.
如果胶卷着火  形成一股热浪  砰
If there's a fire, you'll go up in smoke.
-多有意思  -一块煤炭
"And turn into a piece of charcoal."
小子  你说的什么话
You've got a big mouth.
总有一天割掉你的舌头
One of these days I'll cut it off.
就是这样
Like that.
我可以拿走吗
Can I have it?
Please can I have it?
-我可以拿走吗  -不行
Well, can I or not?
妈的  你是聋子吗
Are you deaf or something?
你应该把这个放在卸下的胶卷里
I have to splice it back before I return the film.
你连只跳蚤都不如
You're such a pest!
那么这些  为什么你卸下这些胶卷的时候不放在那里
Then why didn't you splice these before you returned the films?
因为有些时候我找不到原先的地方了  所以留在这里
Well, sometimes I can't find the right place, so they stay here.
因为  他们亲太多次了
They kiss too much, anyway.
-那我可以拿走这些  -不  听我的  过来
- Then I can have these. - Now you listen to me.
放那
在我踢你屁股一脚之前  我们定个协议
Let's make a deal, before I kick you up the arse.
这些碎片都是你的  我送给你  -谢谢  -不用谢
- All these are yours, a present. - Thank you.
首先你不能再来这  其次这些我拿着  -你明白了没  -好吧
But first, you don't come here again. Second, I keep them here. Get it?
就这么定了  现在离开
OK, so we're agreed. Now, scram!
什么鬼协议
What kind of deal is that?
如果这些是我的  为什么应该你拿去
If they're mine, how come you keep them?
别再让我看见你  否则我劈开你的脑袋
Don't come back or I'll thrash you!
先开枪再思考
"Shoot first, think later.
这里没有给娇弱的人的工作  戴绿帽子的叛徒
"This is no job for weaklings, cuckolds and traitors.
你  下流的混蛋  把手从黄金上拿开
"Hey, you bastard! Hands off that gold!
肮脏的黑鬼  离我远点
"Stay away from me, you dirty swine …
否则我打烂你的脸
"… or I'll smash your face in!"
妈
如果战争结束了  爸爸为什么不回来
If the war's over, why doesn't Dad come back?
会回来的  总有一天会回来  就这几天
He'll come back, you'll see. One of these days.
我都不记得他了  俄国在哪里
I don't remember him anymore. Where is Russia?
到那里需要很多年  然后很多年回来
It takes years to get there … and years to come back.
现在去睡觉  多多  很晚了
Go to bed, Toto. It's late.
快走
你母亲可以不介意  我不行
You can fool your mother, but not me.
拿到证书然后去当宪兵  真倒霉  你这个蠢货
Get your piece of paper and join the police, you little wretch!
我们走  快走
Come on!
那么  5乘5等于多少
Well? How much is 5 x 5?
30.
安静  5的乘法表  蠢货
Quiet! The five times table, you dimwit!
1乘5得5
1 x 5 = 5.
2乘5得10
2 x 5 = 10.
3乘5得15
3 x 5 = 15.
4乘5得20...  够了
4 x 5 = 20.
5乘5
5 x 5?
40.
安静  安静
Quiet! Quiet!
博加  博加
Boccia!
25  25
25.
你永远找不到工作
最后一次
For the last time …
5乘5得多少  圣诞节
- 5 x 5? - Christmas!
不
我买票了  我应该看电影
I've a ticket, I want to see the film.
从这下来  我跟你说多少次了
Get down. You can't stay here.
这里不能待  去影厅
Go back to your seat!
好吃懒做的叛徒  比兔子还差 它们会钻到任何地方
They're all over the place, like rabbits.
我应该去俄勒冈  您为什么不去我的车厢等我
I must go to Oregon. Wait for me at my ranch.
我等待死亡
Wait for a dead man?
汇集了一群杰出演员的奇迹
A star-studded cast
约翰·韦恩  克莱尔·特雷弗  让您度过难忘的时刻
featuring John Wayne, Claire Trevor …
一段发疯的爱情
当世界荒无人烟的时候
大家晚上好  我不能问候吗
Good evening, everyone! Can't I say hello?
今天我们播放两部影片  跟我没关系  我来睡觉的
- Double-bill today. - So what? I come here to sleep.
你决定了吗
-美国人  -来这
减掉它  艾佛特
Cut the news, Alfredo!
意大利不会忘记  抵抗集会
ITALY DOESN'T FORGET. RESISTANCE RALLY.
安静  这些很重要
Quiet! This is important.
一个有污点的起义的民族
The men and women who fought in the Resistance
聚集在罗马的意大利剧院  由CVL[自由志愿军]和ANPI[意大利民族游击组织]宣布了
are reunited in Rome for the First Resistance Rally
反抗军的第一次议会  帕里在总统的桌子前
organised by CVL. Prime Minister Parri …
祝各位身体健康
Hello, everybody!
这部影片还放吗  你该闭嘴了
- Can we watch the film or what? - You shut up, then.
大地颤抖 -海洋插曲
THE EARTH TREMBLES — EPISODE OF THE SEA
西西里岛渔民
Featuring SICILIAN FISHERMEN
小心
说的什么
What does it say?
不知道  我是文盲  -你也是吗  -是
- Who knows? I'm illiterate. - You too?
西西里岛的穷人不讲意大利语
The Italian language is not spoken by the poor in Sicily.
12个小时累到骨子里
12 hours of blood and sweat
什么都带不回家  只足够不饿死
to take home the bare minimum required not to die of hunger.
还有渔网
And yet, their nets
当他们收网的时候还是满的
were full when they pulled them up.
离开海的时候就这样了  这我们都知道
All day fishing, and what do we have to show for it?
也许是这样
That may be so
但是我们能做什么呢？
but what can we do?
我就知道！
I knew it!
20年来我从未在电影院看见过接吻
20 years going to the cinema, and I've never seen a kiss!
从未  从未
Will we ever?
混蛋
Son of a bitch!
剧终
THE END
-我呢  -你
你去找斯大林要工作吧
You? Get a job from Stalin.
去找斯大林  真倒霉
Don't you worry, his day will come.
-你们来工作  -总是对我这样
I always get left out.
很棒的影片  小伙子干的不错
Nice film. That young man worked ever so hard.
可惜运气不好
Pity he was so unlucky.
但是谁给他买的小船
Why did he go and buy that boat?
你什么都不懂
他妈的
Idiot! You didn't understand anything.
所以  小伙子们  为了能明白  从日出工作到日落
Right, boys. Here you work from dawn to dusk.
不要问我能挣多少
And no questions about pay.
妈
我找了你一整天  -牛奶你买了没  -没
I've been looking for you all day. Did you buy the milk?
钱呢
And the money?
被偷了
Stolen.
-你买电影票了吧  -对
You went to the cinema?
电影票  电影票
The cinema!
夫人  怎么了  -别打了  -小孩子都这样...
- Signora Maria, wait! - Leave him alone, you're hurting him.
-什么小孩子  -为什么说蠢话  我们不是让你免费进的吗
And you, why do you tell lies? You know you got in free.
告诉你母亲
Go on, tell your mother.
钱也许掉在里面了
Maybe he lost it inside. How much?
-你原来有多少钱  -50里拉
50 lire.
你今晚在椅子中间找到什么了
What did you find under the seats tonight?
一把梳子
A comb …
两个鞋后跟上的胶皮掌
two heels …
一个鼻烟盒...
a tobacco pouch …
和
And …
50里拉
50 lire.
看见没
See?
谢谢  谢谢  艾佛特叔叔
Thank you, Alfredo. Good night.
-晚上好  -日安  晚安
- Good morning. - Good night.
我们走吧  来吧
我懂了
I understood right away.
广场是我的  是我的广场  我的
The square is mine!
我的午夜  走开  滚  我应该关闭广场
It's midnight! Out! I must close the square.
走开  滚
我的广场 我的
您走路累吗  神父
Hard on the feet, eh, Father?
去的时候是下坡...  所有的圣人都帮你
Going, it's downhill and all the saints help you.
但是回来的时候圣人们觉得帮够了
Coming back, the saints just watch.
-明白  -上帝凭意愿行事
If it is God's will …
-再见  晚上见  -晚上见
See you tonight.
-哪里受伤了  -脚
What's wrong? Your foot this time?
什么事都发生在你身上了
Always something.
我能...  我能做什么
Oh dear, what can we do?
艾佛特  -你认识我父亲吗  -怎么不认识
Did you know my father, Alfredo?
当然认识
Of course I knew him.
又高又瘦让人喜欢  并且有胡子  像我一样
Tall, thin, good-tempered, with a moustache like mine.
他总是笑  长得像克拉克·盖博
He always smiled. He looked like Clark Gable.
-艾佛特  -什么事  我现在更大了  都要五岁了
Now I'm older, Alfredo, and I'm in the fifth year,
我是说我可以去放映间  但是为什么我们不能成为朋友呢
I'm not asking to go into the booth, but couldn't we at least be friends?
我通过外表选择朋友  和聪明的人做敌人
"I choose my friends for their looks, and my enemies for their intelligence."
你作为我的朋友太狡猾了
You're too clever to be my friend.
小子  我一直对我的孩子们说
I always tell my children
注意选择正确的朋友
to be careful how they choose their friends.
怎么说  你没有孩子
But you don't have any children.
当我有孩子的时候我会说
But when I do, I'll tell them.
要疯了
血一样的打击
别哭啦  我在这  别哭啦  没有火了
Don't cry. It's all right, I'm here.
没有火了  我在呢
The fire's out.
-好好的  -妈妈  怎么了
Mum, what happened?
真倒霉
You scoundrel!
要不是我在这  你妹妹差点被烧死  都是你的错  小混蛋
Your sister could have burned to death because of you!
你是我的灾难
You'll be the end of me!
我跟你说过  不要放在枕头底下 放在床边
I told you not to keep your films near the fire.
连照片都烧了
You even burned my photos.
我要杀了你
这个胶卷癖  就像闪电一样
- You and your films! - He was burning down the house.
我一点都不同意
和一个小孩子玩在一起你不觉得羞愧吗
Aren't you ashamed of playing games with him at your age?
关我什么事  我有什么错  那些胶片都是你给的吧
- What have I done? - Who gave him the films?
向我发誓再也不给他这些恶心的东西  这些令人发疯的东西  疯子
You shouldn't give them to him, he's mad!
只谈论胶卷和艾佛特
All he talks about is you and the cinema.
向我发誓再也不让他进电影院  发誓
Swear you won't let him in again.
我向您保证  玛利亚女士
I give you my word.
这位先生应该感谢我  等你的父亲回来他也要打你了
May God send your father home, he'll deal with you.
爸爸再也不会回来了  我知道  他死了
Dad is not coming back, and I know why. He's dead.
不是真的  不
No, it's not true!
我要让你看着他回来
He'll be back, you'll see.
妈妈
人的善恶就这样来了又去，时间如流水
"And so the good and evil of men comes and goes, and time is like a flowing river."
剧终
THE END
烟瘾太大
They smoke like chimneys.
您应该付票钱 不
Go and buy a ticket!
不
圣母啊  怎么了  我不给你们点教训  就不配叫我的名字
I'll make mincemeat out of you!
一群混蛋
-安娜女士  -从这进  出...
Signora Anna!
艾佛特
我不进来  你的妻子让我给你带吃的
Don't blame me, your wife told me to bring your lunch.
给我  我给妈妈说了
- Give it to me. - I told Mum
你不再给我胶片  不是你的错
you didn't give me the film. It wasn't your fault.
我以为胶片会着火
I thought you were joking when you said
是个玩笑
the film could catch fire.
我只想对你说这个  我走了
I just wanted to tell you. Now I'll go.
多多  过来
Toto … come here.
往前  来这  坐下
Come and sit down.
仔细听我对你说  我做这个工作10年了
Now, listen. I started this job when I was ten.
当时没有这种现代的机器
We didn't have these modern machines then.
影片是无声的
Films were silent.
放映机像这样  用手转动手柄操作
You turned the projector by hand with a crank.
每天都用手柄操作
All day long!
就这样通过手柄
And it was hard, this damned crank.
如果累了  就失去速度了
If you got tired, and slowed down a bit …
一下子...  呜  所有都着火了
everything was burned, in a flash.
那你为什么不教我  现在不用手柄不是更方便了吗
So why don't you teach me, now there's no crank and it's easy?
为什么我不愿意  多多
Because I don't want to, Toto.
你不应该做这个工作
This is no job for you.
就像个奴隶  总是一个人待着
You work like a slave, always alone.
一部影片看上百遍
You watch the same film 100 times. Nothing else to do.
就像个疯子一样和葛丽泰·嘉宝  泰隆·鲍华说话
You end up talking to Greta Garbo and Tyrone Power.
像头驴子一样工作  甚至所有的节日  复活节  圣诞节都错过
Always working. Every holiday, Easter, Christmas …
只有星期五才休息
You only get Good Friday off.
听我说  如果耶稣不被钉在十字架上  连周五都要工作
And if they hadn't put Christ on a cross, we'd work even then.
那你为什么不换工作
So why don't you change jobs?
因为我是个笨蛋
Because I'm stupid.
镇上还有几个人能懂得操作  除了我
Who else around here would be a projectionist? No one.
只有像我一样一小部分人可以做这个工作
It takes an imbecile like me.
然而我运气不佳
It's my luck.
当我小的时候有战争
When I was little, there was the war.
当我长大的时候又有另一场战争
When I grew up, there was another war.
所以 你想当个像我一样的小傻瓜吗  -回答我  -不
So, you want to be a stick-in-the-mud like me?
说得好  多多  说得好  多多
Good boy.
我是为你好才说的
It's for your own good.
这里关上后
Always stuck in here.
夏天热死  冬天冷死
Boiling hot in summer, freezing cold in winter.
呼吸烟和汽油味  最后挣得少的可怜
Breathing in fumes, and earning a pittance.
你一点都不喜欢你做的事吗
Is it all bad?
随着时间习惯了
You get used to it. And then, from up here
当在上面听到电影院人满了
when the cinema is full,
大家愉快地笑  你也感到高兴
you hear people laughing, and that makes you happy.
别人笑的时候你也开心
It makes you feel good.
就像你让他们笑一样
Like you're the one who makes them laugh
他们让你忘记不幸和悲伤
and makes them forget their troubles.
这点我喜欢
That, I like.
我说什么来着  还是白说  你看什么  你看什么呢
You didn't hear a word I said. What are you up to?
给我一个你刚刚耍我的理由
I can't turn my back for a minute.
你母亲说的对  你是个疯子
Your mother is right. You're mad!
他怎么做到的  通过观察学到了不少另一个世界的事
How on earth did he do it? He watches and learns.
多多
我还要告诉收纳员  你再也不能进电影院
I'll tell the manager not to let you in. Did you hear?
我还要告诉阿德尔福神父
And I'll tell Father Adelfio.
缺少一个小神职人员  不能再倒霉了
No more altar boy, you understand?
艾佛特
Alfredo!
-去你妈的  -中了
Get stuffed!
我的天啊  我中了12  我的天啊
I've won! I've won the pools!
那个拿波里人
拿波里人赢得了西沙[一种意大利乐透]
Ciccio from Naples has won the pools!
幸运的小子  那个拿波里人中了12  大家快跑啊
The Neapolitan has won the pools! Come along, quick.
北方人都幸运
These Northerners have all the luck!
广场是我的
The square is mine!
停下  停下  怎么了  你有马虱吗
Keep still! Are the horse-flies bothering you?
你有一堆的虱子  走吧  走吧
You've a louse factory up here. Off you go.
我要给你们一拳  你们想要干嘛  回家  快点
What do you want? Off you go.
一个商人有两个店铺
A shopkeeper owns two shops.
一个卖水果
In one, he sells fruit …
坐下
Be seated.
教授  有外部的考生参加小学毕业考试  进来
Here are the external candidates for the School Certificate.
安静  安静
Quiet!
闭嘴
安静
多多
真倒霉  娼妇的儿子
Rotten little stinker!
多多  帮帮我  安静
- Help me, Toto. - Quiet!
-这个题怎么答  -安静
- I haven't got a clue! - Quiet!
多多
弗朗西斯科·梅沙那
Francesco Messana.
以法律的名义逮捕你
In the name of the law, you're under arrest.
干得好
我就知道会是这个结局
蠢极了  没文化
Son of a bitch! Pencil-pusher!
注意  胶片非常容易着火
This is where it can catch fire.
如果着火  你要迅速弄断这和这
If it does, you cut here and there
不让火蔓延到胶片的卷盘  -明白吗  -是  艾佛特
or the whole reel will burn. Got it?
够了 不能发生
I won't stand for this sort of thing!
你明白哪个地方是明胶了吗
Which side is the gelatine on?
味道好极了
It tastes good.
屏幕
醒醒  艾佛特
这是胶片上的小纸条  -一直保存
These are the invoices. Always keep them safe.
-好的 艾佛特  永远不要忘记
- Yes, Alfredo. - Don't ever forget.
停下  停下
救命  小偷
小偷
这是给你的  从今天起你放置卷盘
This is for you. Today you can load the reels.
好高  这样你就可以单独工作了
- It's so high up. - Now you can do it alone.
别动  别动
Stay still.
-妈的  真漂亮  -给我  给我
What a woman!
孩子们  跟巴比诺告别  他要去德国
Children, say goodbye to Peppino. He's going to Germany.
再见
迪·弗朗西斯科 为什么不想跟你的同伴告别
Why won't you say goodbye to your friend?
我父亲说他是共产党
My father says he's a Communist.
祝福您  妈妈
God bless you, Mum.
他们确定在德国能找到工作吗
- Will he find work in Germany? - Who knows?
走向希望之路
屎一样的地方
Screw this country!
把你和你屁股  还有斯大林带去德国吧
Go and work in Germany, you and your Stalin.
再见妈妈
再见  巴比诺  早点回来
Goodbye, Peppino! Come back soon.
再见
永别了  再见
幸好德国比俄国近
At least Germany is closer than Russia.
六年后  第一次  再次见到春季的模特
After six years, the return of spring fashion.
全新的外观
A fresh new look
不像战时那种浮夸的风格
unlike the pompous styles of wartime.
还好  这些帽子不会让再让人羞愧
我不给你们点颜色看看...
I'll make mincemeat out of you!
-就不配叫我的名字  -没错
去你妈的
关注新闻，写信给我们
LOOKING FOR NEWS, WRITE TO US
在俄国的意大利军队的悲剧  开启了痛苦的另一页
Another sad page in the tragedy of our men in Russia.
国防部公布新的阵亡士兵的名单
The Ministry of Defence has released a new list of Italian dead
加入了到目前为止下落不明的人
until now considered missing.
名单将会在军区公布
The names will be posted by the military authorities.
家属将会直接被军事当局召见
All the families concerned will be notified.
可惜我们不知道那个战争的墓地在哪
Unfortunately, we don't know where he's buried.
这是抚恤金的表格  如果你想签字的话
Here is the pension form for you to sign.
你知道我有一个追求者吗  我没给你说过吗
Hadn't I told you? He's courting me.
他竭力讨好我
Well, he's no oil painting …
不算一个美男子  不过...
出去  出去  我不能再开一场了
Go home, we can't have another show.
已经很晚了  你们能谅解吗  我不能再放另一场了
It's late, can't you understand?
不要推搡  里面没位置了  行行好吧
里面有些人已经看了两遍了  你们不要激怒我
Some people have seen it twice.
我被你们挤下去啦
上呀  我们都在这里等了一个多小时了
We've been waiting an hour.
-让外面安静下来啊  -你们都别吵
明天我们放另一部片子
Tomorrow we'll show another film.
超级棒的西部片  我保证  你们回去睡觉吧
A Western, I promise! Go to bed.
伊尼亚齐奥  你也是  -努奇奥  关门  -真麻烦  这些人能毁天灭地啊
Close the doors. They'll wreck the Paradiso. Hell, even.
所有人都疯了似地靠过来
开门  开门
可是我能做什么呢
What do you want me to do?
我们等了三个小时却被赶走
We've been waiting for hours.
一群不思考的疯子
"The mob doesn't think.
不知道在干什么
"It has no mind of its own."
狂怒 Fury (1936) 美国电影
这是斯宾塞·屈塞在电影《狂怒》中的台词
The great Spencer Tracy said it in "Fury".
那你说怎么办呢
Well, what do you say?
我们有办法让这些可怜的疯子看上电影吗
Shall we let the poor devils see the film?
要如何办到呢  也许吧
I wish we could, but how?
我发现你们不相信我的话  但你们要相信你们自己的眼睛
"If you have no faith in me, have faith in what you see."
现在把该死的屁股从高脚凳上挪开
So, get your arse off that stool.
当心
Pay attention.
嘛咪嘛咪哄
从另一边看
Now we pass through these walls.
去窗边看吧  小朋友
Look out of the window, kid.
艾佛特  棒极了
It's beautiful, Alfredo!
看那里  电影画面出现了
Over there! Look, the cinema!
艾佛特好聪明
谢谢艾佛特
Thank you, Alfredo!
那是谁啊  快回去
那是电影
It's the cinema.
你们撸去吧
Go to hell!
艾佛特  听不见声音啊
There's no sound, Alfredo.
-我们再帮帮他们好吗  -好的  好的
Shall we keep them happy?
-你想下去看吗  -是的
Want to go down?
去吧
过来
-看那里  -我的妈呀
- Come. Look at this. - Oh, my God!
努奇奥
-努奇奥  -在  -半价好了  -好  毕竟是墙面
- Ah, Nunzio! Half price will do. - As you wish.
先生们  票还是要付的
You must buy tickets, folks.
优惠价
Half price.
滚开  广场是大家的  不
Get stuffed! The square belongs to everyone.
广场是我的  流氓们  我是认真的
The square is mine! Don't joke about it, it makes me mad.
一  二
胶片起火啦
艾佛特
快跑
Run!
-你怎么啦  -艾佛特还在里面
Oh, my God, what's happened? I can't believe it.
不  艾佛特
艾佛特  艾佛特
救命  救命
Help!
艾佛特  艾佛特
救命啊
Help!
可怜的艾佛特  如此不幸  太不幸了
Poor Alfredo. What a shame.
烧了  烧了
It's all burned down.
烧了烧了
All burned down!
现在怎么办
What do we do now?
镇上没有娱乐活动了  什么都没了
No more entertainment in the village, nothing.
可是谁有钱重修电影院呢
How can we rebuild all this?
斯巴卡菲克那个那不勒斯人  修葺一新  像新造的一样
Look at Ciccio from Naples. You'd hardly know him.
谁有钱造新的电影院
Who has that kind of money?
新天堂影院
The New Cinema Paradiso!
你们满意吗
往里走  往里走  进去看看
鼓掌吧
真呀真高兴  加油
拍手吧
这座电影院为你们而造
This cinema is for you!
也是为了一个孩子  关于工作年龄限制的问题你们怎么解决的
He's just a boy. What about the child labour laws?
我通过演出协会的朋友拿到了执照
I got a licence through my connections.
-斯巴卡菲克  -但其实我一窍不通
But don't ask me how it works.
表面上放映员是我  其实都是多多干活挣钱
Officially, I'm the projectionist, but the money goes to Toto.
多多  你要时刻注意  千万不要睡着
Stay on your toes, Toto. No falling asleep.
可不要再发生意外了
No more disasters.
照艾佛特教你的做
Do as poor Alfredo taught you.
孩子  上帝保佑你
And God bless you, son.
生活还要继续  高兴起来  放点音乐
What's this? A funeral? Life goes on. Music!
你和那个农夫相爱了
You've fallen in love with that peasant?
也许吧
Maybe.
我打赌他求婚了
And he's asked you to marry him?
是的
于是我们结束了是吧
Then it's all over between us?
混蛋  好极了
What a dish!
以圣父圣子圣灵的名义
还来
那是谁
翻了天了  他们吻上了
My God, they're kissing!
我不看情色电影
I shall not watch pornographic films.
奇奥先生干得漂亮
Bravo, Don Ciccio!
-我在新天堂有一席之地吗  -艾佛特 艾佛特
Any room for me in this new paradise?
艾佛特
多多  结束之后你陪他走  好的  安娜  -艾佛特我先走了  -好的
Bring him home afterwards, Toto. I'm going now, Alfredo.
你能来我很高兴
I'm so glad you're here.
-上学怎么样了  -还不错
How is school?
不过现在我有工作了
Fine, but now I'm working
我可能不去上学了  不  多多
maybe I won't go any more.
绝不要这样做  那样的话你早晚一事无成
Don't do that, Toto. You'll end up with egg on your face.
为什么  这是什么意思
What does that mean?
我想说
It means …
这并不是你的工作
that this is no job for you.
现在新天堂影院需要你
Now the Paradiso needs you
你也需要它  但这不会持久
and you need the Paradiso. But it won't last.
有一天你会去做别的事
One day you'll move on to other things.
别的
Other things.
更重要的事
More important things.
确定更重要吗
Much more important.
是的
我知道的  我现在失明了却看得更多
I know. Now I've lost my sight …
I see better.
看到了之前看不到的事情
Things I never saw before.
多多  这是你的功劳  你救了我的命  我不会忘记这件事
Thanks to you, who saved my life, I'll never forget.
不要用这幅表情
Don't look so gloomy.
我还没再次倒霉呢  -你想试试吗
I'm not gaga yet. Want proof?
-是的  那么来吧  我们举个例子说
Let's see. Right now, for instance …
譬如这时候放映机失焦了  检查下
the film is out of focus. Check it.
不  怎么可能
是真的  艾佛特  真的失焦了  这是怎么做到的
You're right, it's out of focus. How did you do?
这太难解释了
It's difficult to explain.
只有两天了吗  你们想取笑谁  还磨磨蹭蹭干什么  更需要勤加苦练了
Only two days? I don't give a shit about other cinemas.
而这里的人们却在污染我的眼睛
是的  我知道  但就算早上八点表演  我也做不到啊
Even if we open at 8 in the morning, we still can't do it.
镇子很大而我了解你们这些生意人
It's a big place and you know it.
我就给罗马的隆巴多写信
绿老鼠指意大利第205轰炸机编队
让你们见识下绿老鼠的厉害
我叫斯巴卡菲克  不要和我拐弯抹角
I'm warning you. Don't mess with me or you'll regret it.
奇奥先生  我有一个想法
I have an idea, Don Ciccio.
您还记得废弃的旧电影院吗  就在这附近的镇子上
Remember the old cinema in the next village?
和这个有什么关系
那里的放映机都生锈了  但给我三四天我就能修好
The projector's gone rusty but I could easily fix it.
让那里变成干净美丽的场所  你们能从市里面找个放映员来吗
Get the cinema cleaned up, hire a projectionist
我们可以在两个影院同时放《枷锁》
and we show the film in both places.
不要胡说了  哪怕你将一切准备就绪  多多
Don't be stupid. You should know better, Toto.
想来要是我们要求两份
Imagine if I asked for two.
他们至少得把我的头砍下来  然后用来当球踢  呵呵
They'd chop my head off and play ball with it.
谁告诉你我们要两份拷贝了  -啊  不需要吗  -不需要
- Who says we need two copies? - You mean we don't?
我在圣母面前用我儿子起誓好吗
I swore on the Virgin Mary to my son.
可以从摇篮看见睡着的女婴
We see a child asleep in her bed.
罗萨  罗萨
出什么事了
-快拿药过来  -好的
Get something, hurry.
拿点药
律师都告诉我了  现在我都知道了
"The lawyer told me. Now I know."
The lawyer told me. Now I know.
所有人都应该知道真相  是的  所有人都应该知道
"Everyone must know. Yes, everyone must know."
所有人都应该知道真相
Everyone must know.
你  相信我吗
"Do you … believe me?"
你相信我吗
Do you believe me?
是的  我相信你
"Yes. I believe you."
是的  我想你
Yes. I believe you.
我们的家  我梦想的家
"Our own home. How I've dreamt of it!"
-我们的家  -我梦想的家
- Our own home. - How I've dreamt of it!
妈妈  -我的儿啊  -妈妈
Tonino! Mamma! My son!
-妈妈  -妈妈
-我亲爱的妈妈  -妈妈
剧终
The End.
THE END
我不喜欢
我把标题从片尾移到了片头
I cut the end credits to go faster.
加速  博加  给我争取时间实现计划
Bring me Part One, while I show a newsreel
不是一次了  十次  十次
让一让  让一让
-你们就这么给我拷上了吗  -你害怕了吧
你活该  混蛋
博加  到了  这是第一次放映
Here's Part One, Boccia.
你快放  人都坐满了
Hurry! The house is packed.
我能怎么办  我也只有一双手  快 加快手脚  准备放映  扳开开关
What are you doing? Get the bloody thing rolling.
等一会会
人群骚动起来了
People are getting restless.
嘘什么嘘  安静
Bunch of animals! Shut up!
去他的吧
To hell with it!
我再强调下明天早上机器里的胶片要运往乡下
多多  你计划好
When is it starting, Toto? We've got work to do tomorrow.
多多  你在干嘛呢  下面的人都怒了
Toto, what's going on? They're furious.
你在上面还在等什么呢
It's been half an hour.
-我能做什么呢  -谁知道呢
And what do you want me to do?
那混蛋怎么还不来  我要怎么办
Where's that son of a bitch? I'll be ruined.
-都怪你  -你们冷静  不要担心
-吃点东西  保持冷静  -奇奥先生
您知不知道  为了看这部电影  我把我生病的妻子留在床上赶过来了
I'll have you know I left my wife sick in bed in order to watch this film.
结果我还看不到
And I still haven't seen a thing.
如果10分钟内你们还不放电影  就把钱还给我  还给在场的观众
If it doesn't start in 10 minutes, we want our money back.
我拿拐杖戳死你
Or I'll give you a taste of my cane.
冷静  冷静
你们让我说句话  我们这么办
Calm down. Can I say something?
-我让你们看下一次的首映好吗  -不好
I'll show you Part One again.
-你们怎么拒绝呢  -我们想要知道影片结局  我知道结局
- We've seen Part One. - We want to know how it ends.
安静  安静
Quiet!
我已经看过全片了  -我来告诉你们结局  -剧透的闭嘴
I've already seen it. I'll tell you how it ends.
博加  博加
博加你出什么事了
Boccia, what's wrong?
-你真无耻  -多么美妙
- You idiot! - This is good.
继续抽送啊你  爽爆了
Go away! Go.
你在干嘛呢  看电影  你们这些没教养的  够了
What are you doing? Watch the screen, you pigs.
镜头结束了
Behave yourself.
我和你们说过什么  不要再玩火
I told you, it doesn't catch fire.
行动似乎总是迟了一步
Progress always comes too late.
七个兄弟七个新娘
SEVEN BRIDES FOR SEVEN BROTHERS
七首难忘的歌
AND SEVEN UNFORGETTABLE SONGS
工人们
Workers of the world …
工人们做到了
聪明
就这样
插入  慢慢来
Go on, stick it in.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
如果我出血要挤柠檬汁是真的吗  柠檬?
Is it true that if I bleed I should squeeze lemon on it?
你说什么呢  谁告诉你这种傻话的
Where did you get that from, you silly boy?
进来  进来  你很能干
Go on, stick it in. Don't worry.
到底谁和你胡说
Like this, you see?
你看并没有出现任何问题  爽  就这样  继续
See? Nothing happens. Good boy.
现在你是真男人了
Now you're a man.
我说什么男人  你是头牛  一头牛
What am I saying? A young bull, that's what you are.
新来的女生
She's new.
不过没啥不好的
Not bad.
友好吗
She's nice.
她父亲是银行新经理  小人  奢华和舒适?
Her father's a bank manager, a big shot.
这里的人们隔着衬衣撸  为了不弄到手上
Jerks it off with his shirt, not to get his hands dirty.
-博加  动动  -快点
Faster, faster.
-跑起来  -最后一个到的是懦夫
Last one's a sissy.
听着
Excuse me.
怎么了
三年级B班  进教室
你掉了这个
You dropped this.
谢谢  我都没发现  太傻了
Thanks. I hadn't noticed.
我叫萨尔瓦托  你呢  我叫艾琳娜
- I'm Salvatore. And you? - Elena. My name is Elena.
我想说  上次在火车站
I wanted to tell you the other day, at the station …
是的  就是《摩登时代》
果然  我记得这部影片
I know it by heart.
我记得40年代我放这部影片时  那个星期天我的第一任妻子去世
I showed it in 1940, on the Sunday my first wife died.
为了不让电影院关门我被隐瞒了消息一整天
They kept it from me all day so they wouldn't have to close the cinema.
直到最后一场放完我才知道
I only found out at the end.
映入脑海
It's stuck in my mind.
这是我永远不会忘记的
I'll never forget.
这是什么  剪去的胶片吗  你重新剪辑的吗  -是的
What is it? Is it your footage?
-在放什么内容
What do you see?
屠夫解牛
A young bull being slaughtered.
地上全是血  血流成河
A big pool of blood on the ground.
上面还有另一头牛
Another young bull steps over the blood …
正在死去
on its way to its death.
你怎么不说话了  看见什么了
What do you see now? Tell me.
没什么  什么都没看见  全部失焦了
Nothing, it's out of focus.
是个女人吗
A woman.
-啊呀  -就是个女人
It's a woman!
是的
是我在火车站见过的姑娘
Yes, a girl I saw at the station.
她怎么样  怎么样呢
What's she like?
她很友善
She's very nice.
和我同岁  瘦的  拥有栗色长发
My age, slim, with long brown hair.
眼睛蓝蓝的大大的  差不多就这样
She has big blue eyes and a clear gaze.
唇上有个小胎记
A beauty spot on her lip.
不过真的很小  不凑近看不出来的
Tiny one, you only see it close.
她笑起来的时候你是什么感受  我不知道
And when she smiles, you feel … I don't know.
-要怎么说  -爱情
Love.
就是爱情
我理解你  多多
I know how it is, Toto.
蓝眼睛姑娘是最难追的
The blue-eyed ones are the worst.
无论你做什么事  都没法让你和她做朋友  没有多少办法
You can never get close to them, whatever you do.
越有分量的男人  对她的印象越深刻
"The bigger the man, the deeper the imprint.
如果中间夹杂着爱情  就会承受痛苦  因为这是一条没有尽头的路
"And when he's in love, he suffers knowing it's a dead end."
你所说的多么美妙啊  但却是令人痛苦的
It's nice what you say, but sad.
是约翰·韦恩在《山的牧人》里演的电影
It was John Wayne in "The Shepherd of the Hills".
艾佛特  你真是个大滑头
You old sneak!
-你好  艾琳娜  -你好  你为什么要跑
- Hello, Elena. - Hi! Why are you running?
为什么  就是...
Because …
我想告诉你
I wanted to tell you …
你记不记得  就是
You remember when …?
天气真好  不是吗
Nice day, isn't it?
真是好天气呢
Yes, beautiful day.
对不起  我现在要走了  -再见  萨尔瓦托  -再见
Excuse me, I must go. Bye, Salvatore.
大傻瓜  大傻瓜
What a jerk!
今天天气真好  不是吗  他妈的
"Nice day, isn't it?" How stupid!
你也许不相信
You don't believe me.
但我会成为你生命中的男主角
But I'll be the man in your life.
我确实长得不像马龙·白兰度
I'm not Marlon Brando, I know.
但好好看看我吧  我是如此丑  是吗
But take a good look at me. I'm not that bad, am I?
那么我们再试一次  说不定我能成功呢  你怎么说
Shall I try again? Maybe this time I'll succeed.
-请问哪位
Please may I speak to Elena?
-你是艾琳娜吗  -是我
Is that you, Elena?
-对不起  我没认出你的声音  -我是萨尔瓦托  你记得我吗  -是的
Sorry, I didn't recognise you. I'm Salvatore, remember?
听着  我知道每次我们相遇  我都表现糟糕但我向你发誓我不是这样的
I know I sound like an idiot whenever we meet, but I'm not like that.
只是我看见你就紧张  无法说出正确的话语  我没有勇气告诉你我除了想你还是想你
I can't find the words to say it, but I can't stop thinking about you.
是的  艾琳娜
你是我睡前最后的念想  又是我早上醒来第一个想到的人
I think of you night and day. I dream of you every night.
你总是出现在我的梦里  我知道打电话不合适但是我喜欢你
Sounds silly on the phone, but I love you.
你再不挂电话我就报警了
Stop this, or I'll call the police.
对不起  你说什么  我是艾琳娜的母亲  你个蠢货
- Who's that? - Elena's mother, you cretin.
对不起  女士  我没有想到  我不知道
I'm sorry, madam. I really didn't know …
他妈的
Bloody hell!
我早告诉过你了  你觉得我是胡说八道
I told you. You thought I was kidding you.
但那些蓝眼睛的姑娘的确是最难追的
Take it from me. The blue-eyed ones are the worst.
现在不要再想这件事了  多多  感情这件事是无法明白的
Forget it, Toto. Feelings can never be understood.
也做不了什么让她明白  只能靠你的花言巧语  大概就是你之前做的那样
- You can't explain them. - Oh, you made the world!
多多  冷静  别置气  我只说说而已
Hey, don't get angry with me. What's come over you?
多多  来这里  多多  你在哪
- Out of the way. You mad? - Toto, come here!
我没法自己走路啊
Can't see where I'm going.
又这样  你得好好注意你的言行
How dare you talk to me like that?
不是赞美天主
With all due respect to the Lord,
他用来两三天就创造了世界
who made the world in three days.
我浪费了一些时间
I'd have taken longer,
但有些事情  不谦虚的说  变得更好了
but certain things I could have done better.
你发现我怎么说的了么  你总是要回应所有人
Like I said, you have all the answers.
我希望你快乐  多多  现在我给你讲一个故事
I'll tell you a story. Just for you, Toto.
我们坐一会  哎哟  太难了
Let's sit down. God Almighty!
有一次
Once upon a time …
一个国王进行宴会
a king gave a feast.
王国里最美的公主们都来参加了
The most beautiful princesses were there.
够了
一个守卫的士兵
A soldier who was standing guard
看见了国王的女儿
saw the king's daughter go by.
她是最美的  他立刻爱上了她
She was the loveliest one, and he fell instantly in love.
但是他只是一个贫穷的士兵  怎么比得上国王的女儿
But what is a simple soldier next to the daughter of a king?
告诉了她没有她自己活不下去
and told her he could no longer live without her.
公主对他强烈的感情十分感动
The princess was so taken by the depth of his feeling
就告诉士兵说
that she said to the soldier,
如果你有耐心...
"If you can wait for 100 days
在我的阳台下等100个白天和夜晚
"and 100 nights under my balcony
那我就是你的了  作死
"I shall be yours."
士兵立刻照做  等了1天  2天
With that, the soldier went and waited one day, two days
10天  20天...
then ten, twenty.
每天晚上公主都从窗户了查岗  士兵从不动摇
Each evening the princess looked out, and he never moved!
无论风雨还是大雪  一直在那里
Always there, come rain, come thunder.
哪怕鸟拉屎  哪怕蜜蜂蜇  他都站着不动
Birds shat on his head, bees stung him, but he didn't budge.
在90个夜晚以后
After 90 nights …
他已经变得
he had become …
又瘦又苍白  不成人样
all dry and pale.
大家无法抑制地流下了
Tears streamed from his eyes.
感动的泪水
He couldn't hold them back.
士兵由于缺觉已经没有力气了
He didn't even have the strength to sleep.
而公主一直看着他
And all that time, the princess watched him.
直到第99个夜晚
When the 99th night came
士兵站了起来
the soldier stood up,
放好了凳子  走了
took his chair, and left.
这就是结局啊  多多
Right at the end, Toto.
不要问我这个故事的意义  我不知道
Don't ask me what it means, I don't know.
如果你明白了  记得告诉我
If you can figure it out, you tell me.
好吧
拜托你  不要问我为什么
Please, don't ask me why.
-艾佛特  有什么事吗  -阿德尔福神父  我要施行圣事
What is it, Alfredo? Not now, I must administer the sacrament.
-阿德尔福神父  -什么  我急需您的帮助  因为...
Father Adelfio, I need you urgently.
-因为我有个疑惑  -什么疑惑  -一个让我灵魂振动的巨大疑惑  -灵魂吗
I have terrible doubts tormenting my soul.
-神父  我有罪  -这个我们之后再说
- Father, I have sinned. - Do that later.
-你是谁  -停下  拜托你别走  你就不能保持沉默吗
Please, don't turn around.
就当什么事都没发生  -我是萨尔瓦托  -可你在这里做什么
- Just act normal. It's Salvatore. - How did you get in here?
艾佛特  你跟我说的太可怕了  我知道
- That's a terrible thing to say. - I know.
-面包和鱼的奇迹吗  -我总是想到它  -但这怎么可能呢  -怎么可能呢
I've often wondered. How is it possible?
世界末日来了  我妈妈和我爸爸说的  但这是怎么流传出来的呢
It's terrible. Mum told Dad. How could you mistake her voice?
原谅我  艾琳娜  我就是个傻瓜
Sorry, Elena, I was stupid.
但我想谈谈你
But I had to talk to you.
艾琳娜  你太美了
You're beautiful, Elena.
我就想和你说这个
That's what I wanted to say.
每次我遇见你都无法说出完整的句子
I can never find the words when I see you.
因为你的美惊呆了我
I get the shivers.
总之  我对此无能为力
I don't know how other people do it.
我想我爱上你了
But I'm in love with you.
神父  我有罪
Father, I have sinned.
我以圣父圣子圣灵的名义赦免你
I absolve you from your sins
保持平静吧  修女
in the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
你笑起来就更美了
You're even prettier when you laugh.
萨尔瓦托  你对我非常绅士  你对我也很友好
You're very sweet, and I like you.
但我不爱你
But I'm not in love with you.
我不在意  我会等  -什么意思
- It's OK. I'll wait. - For what?
-等到你也爱上我  好好听我说
For you to love me. Listen to me.
所有的夜晚  我工作结束以后
Every night, after work
就到你家楼下等你  全部的夜晚
I'll wait outside your house. Every night.
你什么时候改变主意了  就打开窗户  这样我才能了解
When you change your mind, open your window. I'll understand.
-你现在明白了吗  -是的
You understand now?
我现在终于看清了
Yes … finally, I see the light.
再次警告你不要散播这些异端邪说
Next time, don't talk heresy.
电影院起火你活下来了
You survived the fire in the cinema.
但是永恒之火另当别论  永恒之火中无人生还
But from the eternal fire, no one can save you.
多多怎么不在电影院
What's Toto doing?
这时候已经关门了啊
The cinema is closed at this hour.
大家注意
Attention, please!
还有15秒就新年了
15 seconds to the New Year!
14  13  12
Fourteen, thirteen, twelve,
11  10  9  8
eleven, ten, nine, eight,
7  6  5  4
seven, six, five, four,
3  2  1
three, two, one!
无须担心  他肯定是和朋友们在一起
Don't worry, he must be with his friends.
来吧  我们举杯  -新年快乐  -新年快乐
- Cheers! - Happy New Year!
祝大家新年快乐
Happy New Year.
也祝福多多  是的  也祝福多多
Let's drink to Toto.
萨尔瓦托
多多  开灯
Turn the lights on, Toto!
这是什么  放映机还在运转
Look, the car's still running in.
现在我们怎么回家
How will we get home?
停车  停车
Stop!
天哪  那是我父亲
Oh, my God! It's my father.
下午好  门多拉先生  -下午好  -下午好
Good evening.
女士们  先生们  晚上好
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen.
我们从米兰博览会剧院  转播第48场《拿奖离开还是挑战翻倍》
From Milan, we present "Double or Quit".
向你们介绍迈克  大家好
With Mike Bongiorno.
我是如此的幸运  已经忘了我要讲什么了
I've forgotten what I had to say …
真的不是现场吗
You pulling my leg?
可这电视是如何在没有胶片的情况下运转的呢
How can you watch TV without a film?
就是这样的  艾佛特  什么都没有
You just can, Alfredo.
如果买了电视机  就可以在家舒服地看电视了
You can even buy a TV set and watch it at home.
是的  但我不喜欢  我仿佛闻到了烧焦味
This may be so, but I don't like it. I can smell a rat.
-马齐那亚  -是的  就是马齐那亚
马萨-卡雷拉省边上的小镇吗
I guess it's a village near Massa Carrara?
不  卢卡省的
No, it's near Lucca …
经理你看出来这是多么好的创意了吗
Great idea, don't you think?
但没有贷款我哪来的钱买设备  如果我们不组织
Couldn't have bought the equipment without a loan from your bank.
就会和木偶戏是一样的结局
Times have changed.
这种新机器叫电视
It's a new machine. A teleprojector.
-总之您是一个地产商  -是的  地产商
- So, you are a landowner. - Yes, I am.
我明白了  听着  今晚表演什么
What's your area of expertise?
-《神曲》  -《神曲》  有请
- "The Divine Comedy". - Very well.
也许你父亲不满意我的工作  我家境贫穷  是因为这个吗
Maybe your father doesn't like what I do. He thinks I'm poor.
艾琳娜
我在  学校放假了我们要去托斯卡纳
We're going to Tuscany in the summer.
你要是爬上来的话我们就能悄悄见面了
If you came, we could meet in secret.
今年夏天我们公开吧  见不到你我要怎么办
I'm working at the outdoor cinema. I'll miss you.
你不会寂寞的  我每天给你写信
Don't be sad. I'll write every day.
我非常喜欢你  夏天结束我就回来了
I'll be back at the end of summer.
艾琳娜
影片在皇家剧院继续播出
Outdoor cinema tonight at the Imperia.
我们走吧  最后一个到的是傻瓜
Last one's a sissy!
满座
Standing room only!
免费入场  出场付钱
You get in free and pay to leave.
像我这样的年轻男子  健康强壮
请进  才刚开始  票拿在手上
Come on in, the show's just started. Have your tickets ready.
亲爱的萨尔瓦托  没有你的日子特别漫长
Salvatore, my love. The days are never-ending here.
到处都是你的名字  不管是读书  填字  还是看报纸
I see your name everywhere, in books, crosswords, newspapers.
你总是在眼前
You're always before my eyes.
今天有一个坏消息
Sadly, I have bad news.
10月末我们要搬到巴勒莫去
We're moving to Palermo, because of university.
我们不能每天见面了  但是别怕
It'll be difficult to see each other, but don't worry.
一有机会我就来找你  去天堂电影院
I'll come and see you at the Paradiso.
如果我早知道的话，我今早就换裤子了
If only I'd have known, I'd have changed my pants this morning.
-你们准备好了吗  -好了
- Are you ready? - Of course.
我对女人有直觉
I knew she was easy.
-谁来帮我一下  -马上
- Guys, who's going to help me out? - Coming!
我抓到了一条章鱼
Hey, I caught an octopus!
怎么每天都有你的信
Post for di Vita. Every blessed day. Here!
嫉妒吗  可不就是嘛
Hey, don't mess around.
我瞎了
艾琳娜  艾琳娜  艾琳娜
记住我们  还有我们在你酒窖里酿的酒
Remember us and the wine we produced in your cave!
乌利塞  闭嘴  少狂妄自大
- Ulysses, he'll know where we are. - Stop it, don't be scared.
现在谁做主  只有乌利塞
Who is the boss now?
上帝凭借力量  还是人类凭借智慧  站起来  欢呼吧
God with His might, or man with his wit?
我要杀了你们
卑鄙小人
这个讨厌的夏天什么时候才能结束
When will this bloody summer end?
电影里早就结束了
In a film, it'd already be over.
淡出  切到暴风雨  不是很好吗
Cut, and there's a storm. Great!
吓
下雨了
告诉他们我是乌利塞
Tell them I'm Ulysses!
乌利塞
艾琳娜  你什么时候...
Elena! But when …?
我今天回来的  你想象不到我找了什么借口才来到这里
Today. You can't imagine the excuses I made up.
索菲娅·罗兰还是那样
Sophia Loren is always Sophia Loren.
修长的腿  丰满的胸
Long legs and great boobs.
就像拉娜·特纳。-更漂亮
- Like Lana Turner. - More beautiful.
-奇奥先生  -什么
这是的多多的  交给他  这是什么
- For Toto. You give it to him. - What is it?
犹大之血  怎么办  怎么办
The devil take me! What will I do now?
他们说什么
What did they say?
作为战争遗孤  我本来不用服军役
That as a war orphan, I'm exempt from military service.
但是他们可能弄错了  没办法了
But nothing doing — clerical error.
我星期五早上要去罗马  他们说10就会让我退役  过来
Must go to Rome on Friday. They say I'll be discharged in ten days.
萨尔瓦托  你最好离开  我爸爸来了  这样最好  我们可以谈谈
- You should go. My father's here. - Good, I'll talk to him.
我这次一定会说服他
This time I'll convince him.
他不会被说服的  他有其他安排
No, Salvatore. He has other plans for me.
-谁
Who?
-他同事的儿子
The son of a colleague of his.
别这样  我们之后再谈  星期四在天堂电影院等我
We'll talk about it on Thursday. Wait for me at the Paradiso.
我坐5路车来  我爱你
I'll get the 5 o'clock bus. I love you.
多多  这是个好电影
It's a good film, Toto.
但我不懂  放一天就够了
But people here don't understand it.
今晚拜托直接放明天的影片吧  这样新人好接手  好的
Tonight, load tomorrow's reels, ready for the new man.
开心点  我等你  别担心
Hey, cheer up! I'll wait for you, don't worry.
工作还是你的
No one's taking your job.
我会等你  知道吗  不要这样  开心点
It'll be waiting for you. Don't look so gloomy.
我也不知道这对你是好消息还是坏消息
什么消息
您丈夫过世了...
你不会是在等我吧
You were expecting someone else?
没有  我是来帮你的
No, Alfredo. I came down to help you.
不  是在等她吧
No, you were waiting for her.
一个人等多无聊  两个人好点吧
Not nice waiting alone. I'll keep you company.
还是你希望我离开
Maybe you'd rather I went.
你别走  我需要你的帮助
No, don't go. In fact, I need your help.
我只听声音
I can't hear this.
开门  艾琳娜
Open up!
开门  艾琳娜  艾琳娜
Open up! Elena!
奥尔多
剧终
THE END
烂片
我喜欢  我喜欢
I like it!
多多
我在这儿
I'm here.
你之前去哪了  不要害怕  我在  你去哪了
Where were you? Where did you go?
冷静  坐
Calm down. Here, sit down.
-她来了吗
Did she come?
-没人来
No one came.
第三营第九连  通讯兵迪·维塔·萨尔瓦托报道
Salvatore di Vita reporting for duty.
上校  我的退伍令下来了吗
I wish to know when I'll be discharged, sir.
还没有接到通知  便步走
No news as yet. Dismissed.
她父亲搬家了吗  怎么可能  没人知道她家搬去哪了吗
Her father's been transferred and no one knows where to?
混蛋  你根本不想帮我
Sod you, bastard! You won't bloody well tell me, will you?
这个地址不知道
NOT KNOWN AT THIS ADDRESS
上校我本来只用服10天役的  已经一年了  我没回过一次家
I should have done ten days and it's been a year, sir.
至少给我放个假吧
Without a day's leave.
迪·维塔  你的退伍令已经下来了
Di Vita, you've been discharged.
过来
你瘦了
You've lost weight.
过得不好吗
They didn't treat you very well, did they?
他们说你从不出门  也不和人讲话  为什么
They say you never go out or talk to anyone. Why?
你知道为什么
You know how it is.
迟早会这样
Sooner or later, the time comes
不管你说不说  都是一样的
when it makes no difference whether you talk or not.
所以你最好闭嘴
So you might as well shut up.
这里好热
It's hot in here.
多多  带我去海边吧
Take me to the sea.
圣诞节的时时候  一个中尉掐了一个女孩的屁股
At Christmas, this lieutenant pinches a girl's bum.
那个女孩是上校的女儿
She turns round. It's the colonel's daughter.
中尉惊恐地说
Terrified, he says,
如果你的心像你的屁股一样硬  那我就死定了
"If your heart is as hard as what I've just felt, I'm a dead man."
你后来见过她吗
Have you seen her?
没有
没人知道她在哪
No one knows where she is.
或许是注定的吧
It was probably meant to be like this.
每个人都在追寻一颗星星
Each of us has a star to follow.
你现在想做什么呢
And now … what are you planning to do?
你听我说
Listen to this one.
有一次长官对军士说
The commander says to the sergeant,
你记得那边以前有个风车吗
"Remember when there was a windmill there?"
长官  我记得
"Yes, sir. I remember.
现在风车没有了  但是风永远都在
"The windmill's gone, but the wind's still there."
你记得那个士兵和公主的故事吗
Remember the story about the soldier and the princess?
现在我明白士兵最后为什么离开了
Now I understand why the soldier left right at the end.
是的  只要再坚持一晚公主就是他的了
One more night and the princess would have been his.
但是如果公主没有遵守诺言
But she might not have kept her promise.
那就太糟了  他会痛苦死的
That would have been too cruel. It would have killed him.
至少在那99晚里  他都觉得她在等他
This way, at least, for 99 nights he lived in hope that she'd be his.
像士兵一样  离开吧  多多
Do as the soldier, Toto. Go away from here.
这是不幸之地
This land is cursed.
每天生活在这儿  会觉得自己是世界的中心
Living here every day, you think it's the centre of the world.
会觉得什么都不会变
That nothing will ever change.
然后离开  一年  两年
Then you leave, for a year or two.
回来的时候什么都变了
And when you return everything's changed.
线断了
The thread is broken.
找不回你想找寻的  你想要的都不在这里了
You don't find what you were looking for. What was yours is gone.
要离开很久  很多年
You need to go away for a long time, for many years
再来找寻你的朋友
before you can come back and find your people …
你出生的土地
the land where you were born.
但是现在不可能
But not now. It's impossible.
你现在比我还瞎
Now you're blinder than I am.
这是谁说的  贾利·库珀  詹姆斯·史都华  还是亨利·方达
Who said that? Gary Cooper? James Stewart? Henry Fonda?
不  多多
No, Toto.
这不是台词
No one said it.
这是我想说的
This time, I'm saying it.
生活不是电影
Life is not what you see in films.
生活更艰难
Life is much harder.
你走吧
Go away!
回罗马去  你还年轻
Go back to Rome. You're young.
世界都是你的
The world's your oyster.
我老了
I'm old.
我不想再听你讲话了
I don't want to hear you any more.
我想听别人谈论你
I want to hear about you.
不要回来了
Don't come back.
不要想我们  不要回头  不要写信
Don't think about us. Don't look back, don't write.
不要妥协  忘了我们
Don't give in to nostalgia. Forget about us.
如果你坚持不下去要回来  不要来找我
If you come back, don't come and see me.
我不会让你踏进家门  懂了吗
I won't let you in, you understand?
谢谢
Thank you …
谢谢你为我做的一切
for everything you've done.
不管做什么工作  都要热爱它
Whatever you end up doing, love it.
像你爱影院的放映机一样
The way you loved the projection booth
当时你真淘气
when you were a little boy.
已经出发了吗  多多  永别了
Is he already gone? Toto, farewell!
永别了
多多
我来晚了  好遗憾
I'm too late, what a pity!
是多多  我知道是他
It's Toto. I knew it.
-多多  -你还好吗  妈妈
你妹妹会很高兴的
Your sister Lia will be so happy to see you. And the children.
孩子们都不认识你了  他们长大了
You won't recognise them.
他们总是写信告诉我想来罗马
When are they coming to Rome?
你知道现在家里有多漂亮吗
See how nice the house is?
我们整修过  多亏了你
We've had it all redone, thanks to you.
过来  我有个惊喜给你
Come, I've a surprise for you.
你累了吧
Are you tired?
要休息吗  葬礼之前都可以
You've time to rest before the funeral.
不了  妈妈  一个小时后的飞机
No, Mum. The flight is only an hour.
这么多年了  不能说走就走
Don't say that, after all these years.
过来  我把所有东西都放这里了
Come, I've put all your things in here.
你来了他会很高兴的  多多
He must be glad you came, Toto.
他总是谈起你  总是
He always talked about you, always.
直到最后一刻  他想你...
Right up to the end.
他很想你
He really loved you.
他给你留了两样东西
He left something for you.
走之前
Before you leave
来找我
come and see me.
-谁啊  -是他  是他
早安
关门多久了
When did you close it down?
到五月就六年了  没有人来了
Six years ago in May. No one ever came.
您比我更清楚  经济危机  电视  磁带...
You know it better than I do. The recession, TV, videos …
电影只存在于梦里了
The cinema has become a memory.
现在政府买下它作为停车场
The city has purchased the site for a public car park.
星期六就要拆掉了  真遗憾
They're pulling down on Saturday, Signor di Vita. Pity!
你为什么称我为"您"
Why "Signor di Vita?"
以前不是这样的
It didn't use to be like that.
称一个重要人物为"你"太困难了
It's awkward to be casual with an important person.
但是如果你坚持  我还是叫你多多吧
However, if you insist … Toto.
失陪
Excuse me.
谁能想到呢  多多
Who would have believed it? Toto.
舅舅  下次外婆去罗马的时候  我也想去
Uncle, next time grandma goes to Rome, I'll go with her.
我想看看你在做什么
I want to see where you work.
好啊  但其实没什么好看的
OK, but there's not much to see.
我总是雷声大雨点小
My job is much ado about nothing.
你可别上当
Careful, Salvatore.
他们俩比食人者还坏
They're worse than cannibals, they'll take advantage of you.
舅舅  你明天出发吗
Are you off tomorrow?
我不知道  我真的不知道，菲利波
I don't know. I really don't know, Filippo.
应该是找你的
Must be for you.
整个下午都在打电话  他们想知道你今晚还是明天出发
They've been ringing all day asking when you'll be back.
两杯威士忌
Double whisky, please.
对对  是他
请问你是洛林先生吗  我是你的粉丝
Excuse me, aren't you Dr Lénera? I'm a fan of yours.
谢谢你
Thank you.
小姐
怎么了
不好意思  我认错人了
I'm so sorry, I thought you were someone else.
总是我给你打电话
为什么是现在
It's always me ringing.
我告诉过你中午来接我
I asked you to pick me up at lunchtime.
我不去
Forget it, I'm not going.
不用管我了  我自己走
In fact, I'll go on my own.
多多  你在想什么
What are you thinking, Toto?
我在想...  我们从没有聊过天
We've never really talked, Mum.
小时候我觉得
When I was little, I saw you …
你已经老了
as an old woman already.
可能所有子女都会这样
Maybe all kids are like that, who knows?
但是现在我才发现
It's taken me all this time …
那时你很年轻  很漂亮
to realise that you were young then, and beautiful.
有美好的人生
You had your whole life ahead of you.
但是你为什么总是一个人
Why, then? Why did you stay on your own?
没有和别人在一起
Without anyone to look after you.
你本可以再婚的  为什么没有呢
You could have remarried. Why didn't you?
那时候我不懂
I might not have understood at the time.
后来明白了
But later … yes.
我没有和任何人在一起过
There was never anyone, if that's what you're thinking.
我不想
I didn't want to.
我总是很忠贞  对你父亲
I remained faithful, first to your father
对你  对丽娅
and then to you and Lia.
我只能做到这样
It's the way I am, what can I do?
你很像我
And you're like me.
对你热爱的事物很忠诚
You're too attached to the past.
我不知道这是否是好事
I'm not sure it's a good thing.
忠诚是一个很可怕的东西
Being faithful has its drawbacks.
如果你忠诚  你就会永远一个人
Fidelity brings loneliness.
我不该给你打电话的
I shouldn't have called you.
别管他们了
It's not your fault, Mum.
我总是害怕回来
I've always been afraid to come back.
这么多年过去了
Now, after all these years …
我以为我会更坚强  会忘记很多事
I thought I was stronger and had forgotten many things.
但是  所有事都浮现在眼前
But it's all right there in front of me …
似乎我从未离开
as if I'd never gone away.
但是我看着丽娅就好像是陌生人
And yet, I hardly know Lia.
还有你  妈妈
And you, Mum …
我抛弃了你
I deserted you.
我像强盗一样逃走了
I ran away like a criminal.
从未给你解释
Without an explanation.
我不需要解释  你不需要解释
I never asked for one. You don't have to explain.
我觉得你做的是对的
I always thought you were doing the right thing.
不用去追究
Don't dwell on it.
只有一件事让我痛苦
Only one thing bothered me.
夜晚睡觉前
At night, before I went to bed,
关门的时候
I'd lock the door.
你以前不关门的
- You never used to. - I know.
不是的  你以前晚上在电影院工作
When you worked in the cinema, late at night,
你不回家  我都睡不着
I could never sleep till you got home.
当你回到家
Then, when you got back,
我就假装睡着了
I pretended to be asleep.
但是我能感觉到你的所有动作
But I was aware of all your movements.
然后我就起来
Then, when you were asleep, I'd get up
关门
and lock the door.
后来你离开了
After you'd gone …
我每次去关门的时候
whenever I did that
都觉得把谁远远地
I felt as though I was locking someone out.
关在了门外
Shutting him off.
你离开是对的
You were right to leave.
你实现了自己的梦想
It allowed you to do what you wanted.
每次我给你打电话  都是不同的女人接的
When I phone you, it's a different woman every time.
我装作认识她们
I pretend that I know them
不让她们尴尬
to avoid embarrassing introductions.
我肯定她们觉得我是疯子
I bet they take me for a dotty old woman.
但是我至今没有听到  真正爱你的声音
But I haven't yet heard the voice of someone who really loves you.
我明白
I can tell, you know.
我很想看到你安定下来
All the same, I'd like to see you settling down.
和别人相爱
In love with someone.
但你的生活在那里
But your life is there.
这里只有鬼魂
Here, there are only ghosts.
算了吧  多多
Let go, Toto.
博加
Boccia!
他叫罗·梅奥
His name was Lo Meo.
温琴佐
喂
喂  谁啊
Hello! Who is it?
我找艾琳娜女士  我就是
- May I speak to Signora Elena? - Speaking.
谁啊
Who is it?
萨尔瓦托  萨尔瓦托
Salvatore.
谁啊
Who?
我是萨尔瓦托·迪维塔
Di Vita. I'm Salvatore di Vita.
你还记得吗
Remember me?
我在你家楼下的酒吧
I'm ringing from the bar across the road, Elena.
当然记得
Of course I remember you.
我想见你  艾琳娜  我们见面吧
I'd like to see you, Elena. Let's meet.
已经过去很久了
It's been a long time.
为什么要见面呢
Why should we meet?
有什么用呢
What good would it do?
求你了  不要拒绝我
Please, don't say no.
萨尔瓦托  我老了  你也是
I'm old, Salvatore. And so are you.
还是不见面比较好
It's best not to see each other.
再见
喂
萨尔瓦托
你怎么知道我在这里
How did you know I'd be here?
我不知道过去多少年了  但是你的事我都记得
It's been a long time, but I haven't forgotten certain things.
你没有多少地方可去
There aren't many places you'd go to.
我找到了
I did the rounds.
你还是那么美
You're still beautiful.
说什么呢  我老了
What are you saying? I'm old.
不要这样看着我
Don't look at me like that.
你怎么回来了
Why have you come back?
艾佛特去世了  你记得他吗
Alfredo's dead. Remember him?
我当然记得  很遗憾
Of course I remember him. I'm sorry.
你很爱他
You were very fond of him.
我看到你的女儿了
I saw your daughter.
很漂亮
She's very beautiful.
不知道有多少个萨尔瓦托在追她
God knows how many Salvatores she's got in tow.
有人追
A few.
但是叫萨尔瓦托的应该不多
But there are not many Salvatores.
我还有个大儿子
I've a son, too. He's older.
你呢
And you?
我没有子女  也没有结婚
No children. I never married.
你幸福吗
You happy?
总的来看很幸福
I am, all things considered.
虽然和我那时的梦想不一样
Though it's not what I dreamt of.
你认识我丈夫吗
You know my husband, don't you?
怎么不认识  博加
Boccia, I remember him well.
他做什么工作
What does he do? What's his job?
政治  他是区议员
He's a politician. A local councillor.
我们在比萨大学重逢
We met again at Pisa University.
你怎么没和你父亲同事的儿子结婚
How come you didn't marry your father's …?
我不想  最后我赢了
I didn't want to. I got my own way in the end.
然后...我在等你
I was still waiting for you at the time.
但是我从没有忘记你
I never forgot you. Never.
我也是
Neither did I.
虽然你消失了
Even though you'd disappeared.
但是现在说这些有什么用呢
But why talk about it now?
我们只是在冒着可怜又可笑的风险  -你一直住在罗马吗
It's pathetic, and absurd. You still live in Rome?
-你说什么呢
What are you saying?
我们最后一次见面  我们约好在天堂电影院  你记得吗
We'd arranged to meet at the Paradiso.
但是你没来  你什么都没说就消失了
But you never showed up. Not a word, nothing.
多少年过去了  30多年了
How long ago was it? Over 30 years.
但是我…
But I …
我去了那个约会
I did show up.
只是我去晚了
But I was late.
我和我父母吵架了
I'd quarrelled with my parents.
我试着说服他们不要拆散我们
Trying to convince them not to come between us.
但是没有用
But it was no use.
他们决定永远离开西西里
They'd made up their minds to leave Sicily once and for all.
之后这变成了事实
And that's what we did.
我不知道该做什么  说什么
I didn't know what do, what to say.
然后我同意了  做了他们想要的
So I agreed to do what they wanted.
作为交换我爸爸同意我见你最后一面  和你告别
But I convinced my father to let me see you one last time.
我打算只要见到你
I was hoping …
我们就可以一起做决定
we'd take a decision when we met.
我以为也许…
I thought maybe …
我们可以私奔
we'd run away together.
我爸爸陪我去了电影院  但是你不在放映室  只有艾佛特
My father took me to the cinema. But Alfredo was there, not you.
我没有时间等你回来
And I couldn't wait for you to come back.
艾琳娜  快点
Hurry up, Elena.
我告诉艾佛特所发生的事情
I told Alfredo what was happening.
告诉他我当晚就离开  我求他帮我转达
I said we were going away and asked him to let you know.
他人很好
He was very nice to me.
很认真听我讲话  然后...
He listened to me patiently.
冷静点  别这样
Calm down, don't get upset.
听我说
Listen to what I have to say.
如果你想让我向多多转达你说的话  我可以帮你
If you want me to tell Toto, I will.
但是如果你想听我的建议  还是算了吧
But if you want my advice, let it be.
不见面对你俩都好
It's best for you two to stay apart.
亲爱的
My dear child …
火总会燃成灰烬
Out of the fire of love come ashes.
爱也会逝去
Even the greatest love eventually fizzles out.
以后会有更多其他的爱情
You'll meet other people, plenty of them.
但是多多只有一个未来
But there's only one future for Toto.
但是他现在不懂  也不会相信
He doesn't know it yet, and wouldn't believe me if I told him.
甚至会想杀了我
He'd kill me if I did.
但是你能懂
But you, my dear … you can understand.
你必须懂
You must understand. Do it for him.
这个秘密我本来不想告诉你
I never wanted anyone to know my secret, not even you.
可恶的艾佛特
Bloody Alfredo!
他也迷惑了你
He charmed everyone, even you.
我听从了他的建议
I said I'd follow his advice.
但是出发前  我给你留了纸条
But I left a note for you before I left.
我下楼梯时
I was on my way down.
想到艾佛特看不见
I knew Alfredo couldn't see me.
我又回去了
So I went back up.
他坐在放映机前一动不动
I saw him sitting there, by the projector.
我取下一张墙上的纸条
I took one of those bits of paper on the wall.
我给你写了我的地址
And wrote a note saying where to find me.
以及我会等你
And that I'd wait for you.
但是你还是消失了
But you disappeared all the same.
我找了你很多次
If you knew how I searched for you.
你不明白
You can't imagine.
我写过信  打过电话
I wrote, I phoned … nothing.
从来没有人回应
No one ever replied.
所以我逃走了
That's why I left …
再也不回来了
and never came back.
我一直梦见你
But for years I dreamt of you.
尽管时间流逝
Time went by.
在遇见的所有女人中  我只想找到你
Yet I looked for you in every woman I ever met.
我的事业很成功  的确很成功
I was lucky in my career. Very lucky, it's true.
但我总是缺少什么
But something was missing.
我没有想到  造成这一切的
I could never have imagined it would be the fault
是那个我视为父亲的人
of the man who was like a father to me.
疯子
A mad man!
他不是疯子  刚开始我也恨他
He wasn't mad. I hated him at first.
但是后来
But as time went by …
我明白了他的话
I understood his advice.
和你的沉默
And I understood your silence.
但是我从未见过那张纸条
But I never found that note.
我自己盖住了
I covered it with my own hands.
我没有发现  这是唯一的解释
I didn't see it, there's no other explanation.
现在找原因不重要
No point explaining any more.
已经过去了
That's how it was.
艾佛特没有背叛你
But Alfredo didn't betray you.
那是唯一让你想清楚的办法  萨尔瓦托
He knew you better than anyone.
如果你选择了我  就不会拍电影
If you'd chosen to stay with me, you'd never have made any films.
那会有多遗憾
And that would have been a great pity.
都是好电影  我都看过
They're such beautiful films. I've seen them all.
但是你不该改名字
But you shouldn't have changed your name.
你应该叫萨尔瓦托·迪维塔
What's wrong with your name?
这些是他留给你的
He left this for you.
每当电视里播你的电影  他都很开心
When they showed your films on television, he was happy.
他总是坐在那里  度过一切疾病
He just sat in front of the TV and forgot all his ailments.
他记得台词每一句
He knew every single word by heart.
而我给他解说
And I told him what the images were.
当报纸谈论你  我要给他读两三遍
And when you were in the papers, he'd make me read it again and again.
-他从没想过见我吗
He never asked to see me?
-没有
No. Never.
有一次你妈妈告诉我们
Your mother once said
如果他想  你一定会来
you'd come if he wanted you to.
他发火
He was furious. He said,
他说  不行  多多绝不能回来
"No. Toto must never return to Giancaldo."
他没有恶意
He wasn't being mean.
他是一个虔诚的基督教徒
He was a good man.
谁知道他在想什么
Who knows what went through his head?
最后关头也在说一些胡话
He started saying strange things towards the end.
闭眼之前
Just before he closed his eyes …
他让你母亲不要通知你
he told your mother not to let you know.
77  76  68  不
1977, 1976, 1968 …
《白鲸记》[赫尔曼·梅尔维尔小说]
Moby Dick.
《抽屉里的梦》
Dreams in a Drawer.
《挑战》
The Challenge.
《野生之道》
The Searchers.
《妄执》
Magnificent Obsession.
《呐喊》
Il Grido.
"萨尔瓦托  原谅我
"Forgive me, Salvatore.
让我解释发生了什么
"One day I'll tell you what happened.
很糟糕没有找到你
"I'm so sorry I couldn't see you.
但是今晚  我要和我妈妈去托斯卡纳
"Unfortunately, I'm leaving with my mother tonight.
我们要搬走
"We're moving to Tuscany.
但是我只爱你
"But I love only you.
我不会和别人在一起的  我保证
"I'll never love anyone else, I swear.
我给你留了我朋友的地址  你可以给我写信
"I'm giving you the address of a friend for you to write.
不要抛弃我
"Don't ever leave me.
吻你  艾琳娜"
"I love you.
"Elena"
你什么时候出发
When do you leave?
今天下午
This afternoon.
要是以后我们可以...
Elena, maybe in future we can …
萨尔瓦托  我们没有将来  只有过去
There is no future, Salvatore. Only the past.
昨晚见面也只是一场梦
Even what happened yesterday is only a dream.
一场无与伦比的梦
A marvellous dream.
我们年轻时没有实现的梦
We never did it when we were young.
你记得吗
Remember?
现在已经发生了  没有比这更好的结局了
I couldn't have hoped for a better ending.
我不这么想
I'll never agree with you.
永远不会  ————艾琳娜
Never, Elena.
这是我的广场
The square is mine!
检查一下  -准备好就可以开始放
Check the leader. Roll when you're ready.
-好的  -你的电影很赞  -谢谢
OK. Congratulations, I loved your film.
发布会在下午  制片人和演员也会去
There'll be a press conference with the actors, producer …
得奖消息刚刚出来  我们已经收到成堆的电报了
The prize has just been announced and the telegrams are already mounting.
怎么了  你不开心吗
Aren't you happy?
好的  我们待会谈
Yes, of course. We'll talk later.
剧终
THE END